{
    "id": 270,
    "question": "Let $z \\in C$ with $\\operatorname{Im}(z)=10$ and it satisfies $\\frac{2 z-n}{2 z+n}=2 i-1$ for some natural number $n$, then \\\\",
    "reference": "2019 Main, 12 April II",
    "options": [
        "a) $n=20$ and $\\operatorname{Re}(z)=-10$\\\\",
        "b) $n=40$ and $\\operatorname{Re}(z)=10$\\\\",
        "c) $n=40$ and $\\operatorname{Re}(z)=-10$\\\\",
        "d) $n=20$ and $\\operatorname{Re}(z)=10$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(c)",
    "solution": "Let $z=x+10 i$, as $\\operatorname{Im}(z)=10$ (given)\n\nSince $z$ satisfies,\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\frac{2 z-n}{2 z+n} & =2 i-1, n \\in N, \\\\\n\\therefore \\quad(2 x+20 i-n) & =(2 i-1)(2 x+20 i+n) \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\quad(2 x-n)+20 i & =(-2 x-n-40)+(4 x+2 n-20) i\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nOn comparing real and imaginary parts, we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& & 2 x-n & =-2 x-n-40 \\text { and } 20=4 x+2 n-20 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & & 4 x & =-40 \\text { and } 4 x+2 n=40 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & & x & =-10 \\text { and }-40+2 n=40 \\\\\n& \\text { So, } & n & =40 \\text { and } x=\\operatorname{Re}(z)=-10\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 271,
    "question": "All the points in the set $S=\\frac{\\alpha+i}{\\alpha-i}: \\alpha \\in \\mathbf{R} \\quad(i=\\sqrt{-1})$ lie on a",
    "reference": "2019 Main, 9 April I",
    "options": [
        "a) circle whose radius is $\\sqrt{2}$.",
        "b) straight line whose slope is -1 .",
        "c) circle whose radius is 1 .",
        "d) straight line whose slope is 1 ."
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(c)",
    "solution": "Let $x+i y=\\frac{\\alpha+i}{\\alpha-i}$\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow x+i y=\\frac{(\\alpha+i)^{2}}{\\alpha^{2}+1}=\\frac{\\left(\\alpha^{2}-1\\right)+(2 \\alpha) i}{\\alpha^{2}+1}=\\frac{\\alpha^{2}-1}{\\alpha^{2}+1}+\\frac{2 \\alpha}{\\alpha^{2}+1} i\n$$\n\nOn comparing real and imaginary parts, we get\n\n$$\nx=\\frac{\\alpha^{2}-1}{\\alpha^{2}+1} \\text { and } y=\\frac{2 \\alpha}{\\alpha^{2}+1}\n$$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\text { Now, } x^{2}+y^{2}={\\frac{\\alpha^{2}-1}{\\alpha^{2}+1}}^{2}+{\\frac{2 \\alpha}{\\alpha^{2}+1}}^{2} \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\alpha^{4}+1-2 \\alpha^{2}+4 \\alpha^{2}}{\\left(\\alpha^{2}+1\\right)^{2}}=\\frac{\\left(\\alpha^{2}+1\\right)^{2}}{\\left(\\alpha^{2}+1\\right)^{2}}=1 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad x^{2}+y^{2}=1\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nWhich is an equation of circle with centre $(0,0)$ and radius 1 unit.\n\nSo, $S=\\frac{\\alpha+i}{\\alpha-i} ; \\alpha \\in \\mathbf{R}$ lies on a circle with radius 1 .",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 272,
    "question": "Let $z \\in C$ be such that $|z|<1$. If $\\omega=\\frac{5+3 z}{5(1-z)}$, then\\\\",
    "reference": "2019 Main, 9 April II",
    "options": [
        "a) $4 \\operatorname{Im}(\\omega)>5$\\\\",
        "b) $5 \\operatorname{Re}(\\omega)>1$\\\\",
        "c) $5 \\operatorname{Im}(\\omega)<1$\\\\",
        "d) $5 \\operatorname{Re}(\\omega)>4$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Given complex number\n\n\n\\begin{align*}\n& \\omega=\\frac{5+3 z}{5(1-z)} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad 5 \\omega-5 \\omega z=5+3 z \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad(3+5 \\omega) z=5 \\omega-5 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad|3+5 \\omega||z|=\\mid 5 \\omega-5 \\tag{i}\n\\end{align*}\n\n\n[applying modulus both sides and $\\left|z_{1} z_{2}\\right|=\\left|z_{1}\\right|\\left|z_{2}\\right|$ ]\n\n$$\n\\because \\quad|z|<1\n$$\n\n$\\therefore|3+5 \\omega|>|5 \\omega-5|$\n\n\\section*{Complex Numbers}\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\quad \\omega+\\frac{3}{5}>|\\omega-1|\n$$\n\nLet $\\omega=x+i y$, then $x+\\frac{3}{5}^{2}+y^{2}>(x-1)^{2}+y^{2}$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad x^{2}+\\frac{9}{25}+\\frac{6}{5} x>x^{2}+1-2 x$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\frac{16 x}{5}>\\frac{16}{25} \\Rightarrow x>\\frac{1}{5} \\Rightarrow 5 x>1$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad 5 \\operatorname{Re}(\\omega)>1$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 273,
    "question": "Let $-2-\\frac{1}{3} i^{3}=\\frac{x+i y}{27}(i=\\sqrt{-1})$, where $x$ and $y$ are real numbers, then $y-x$ equals\\\\",
    "reference": "2019 Main, 11 Jan I",
    "options": [
        "a) 91\\\\",
        "b) 85\\\\",
        "c) -85\\\\",
        "d) -91"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(a)",
    "solution": "We have, $\\frac{x+i y}{27}=-2-\\frac{1}{3} i^{3}=\\frac{-1}{3}(6+i)^{3}$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\Rightarrow \\frac{x+i y}{27} & =-\\frac{1}{27}\\left(216+108 i+18 i^{2}+i^{3}\\right) \\\\\n& =-\\frac{1}{27}(198+107 i)\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\n$\\left[\\because(a+b)^{3}=a^{3}+b^{3}+3 a^{2} b+3 a b^{2}, i^{2}=-1, i^{3}=-i\\right]$\n\nOn equating real and imaginary part, we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{gathered}\nx=-198 \\text { and } y=-107 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\quad y-x=-107+198=91\n\\end{gathered}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 274,
    "question": "Let $A=\\theta \\in-\\frac{\\pi}{2}, \\pi: \\frac{3+2 i \\sin \\theta}{1-2 i \\sin \\theta}$ is purely imaginary Then, the sum of the elements in $A$ is \\\\",
    "reference": "(2019 Main, 9 Jan I) ",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\frac{3 \\pi}{4}$\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{5 \\pi}{6}$\\\\",
        "c) $\\pi$\\\\",
        "d) $\\frac{2 \\pi}{3}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Let $z=\\frac{3+2 i \\sin \\theta}{1-2 i \\sin \\theta} \\times \\frac{1+2 i \\sin \\theta}{1+2 i \\sin \\theta}$ (rationalising the denominator)\n\n$$\n\\begin{gathered}\n=\\frac{3-4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta+8 i \\sin \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta} \\\\\n{\\left[\\because a^{2}-b^{2}=(a+b)(a-b) \\text { and } i^{2}=-1\\right]} \\\\\n=\\frac{3-4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta}+\\frac{8 \\sin \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta} i\n\\end{gathered}\n$$\n\nAs $z$ is purely imaginary, so real part of $z=0$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\therefore \\frac{3-4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta}=0 \\Rightarrow 3-4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta=0 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad \\sin ^{2} \\theta=\\frac{3}{4} \\Rightarrow \\sin \\theta= \\pm \\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-09}\n\\end{center}\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\quad \\theta \\in-\\frac{\\pi}{3}, \\frac{\\pi}{3}, \\frac{2 \\pi}{3}\n$$\n\nSum of values of $\\theta=\\frac{2 \\pi}{3}$.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 275,
    "question": "A value of $\\theta$ for which $\\frac{2+3 i \\sin \\theta}{1-2 i \\sin \\theta}$ is purely imaginary, is\\\\\\\\",
    "reference": "2016 Main",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\frac{\\pi}{3}$\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{\\pi}{6}$\\\\",
        "c) $\\sin ^{-1} \\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{4}$\\\\",
        "d) $\\sin ^{-1} \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Let $z=\\frac{2+3 i \\sin \\theta}{1-2 i \\sin \\theta}$ is purely imaginary. Then, we have $\\operatorname{Re}(z)=0$\n\nNow, consider $z=\\frac{2+3 i \\sin \\theta}{1-2 i \\sin \\theta}$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\frac{(2+3 i \\sin \\theta)(1+2 i \\sin \\theta)}{(1-2 i \\sin \\theta)(1+2 i \\sin \\theta)} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2+4 i \\sin \\theta+3 i \\sin \\theta+6 i^{2} \\sin ^{2} \\theta}{1^{2}-(2 i \\sin \\theta)^{2}} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2+7 i \\sin \\theta-6 \\sin ^{2} \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2-6 \\sin ^{2} \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta}+i \\frac{7 \\sin \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^{2} \\theta} \\\\\n\\because \\quad \\frac{2-6 \\sin ^2 \\theta}{1+4 \\sin ^2 \\theta} & =0 \\Rightarrow 2=6 \\sin ^2 \\theta \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\quad \\sin ^2 \\theta & =\\frac{1}{3} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\quad \\sin ^2 \\theta & = \\pm \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\quad \\theta & =\\sin ^{-1}\\left( \\pm \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)= \\pm \\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}\\right)\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 276,
    "question": "If $\\left|\\begin{array}{ccc}6 i & -3 i & 1 \\\\ 4 & 3 i & -1 \\\\ 20 & 3 & i\\end{array}\\right|=x+i y$, then\n\\\\",
    "reference": "\n\n$(1998,2 M)$ ",
    "options": [
        "a) $x=3, y=1$\\\\",
        "b) $x=1, y=1$\\\\",
        "(c) $x=0, y=3$\\\\",
        "d) $x=0, y=0$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Given, $\\left|\\begin{array}{rrr}6 i & -3 i & 1 \\\\ 4 & 3 i & -1 \\\\ 20 & 3 & i\\end{array}\\right|=x+i y$\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad-3 i\\left|\\begin{array}{crr}6 i & 1 & 1 \\\\ 4 & -1 & -1 \\\\ 20 & i & i\\end{array}\\right|=x+i y$\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad x+i y=0\\left[\\because C_2\\right.$ and $C_3$ are identical $]$\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\quad x=0, y=0\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 277,
    "question": "The value of sum $\\sum_{n=1}^{13}\\left(i^{n}+i^{n+1}\\right)$, where $i=\\sqrt{-1}$, equals\\\\",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) $i$\\\\",
        "b) $i-1$\\\\",
        "c) $-i$\\\\",
        "d) 0"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "$\\sum_{n=1}^{13}\\left(i^n+i^{n+1}\\right)=\\sum_{n=1}^{13} i^n(1+i)=(1+i) \\sum_{n=1}^{13} i^n$\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n= & (1+i)\\left(i+i^2+i^3+\\ldots+i^{13}\\right)=(1+i)\\left[\\frac{i-\\left(1-i^{13}\\right)}{1-i}\\right] \\\\\n= & (1+i)\\left[\\frac{i(1-i)}{1-i}\\right]=(1+i) i=i-1\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nAlternate Solution\nSince, sum of any four consecutive powers of iota is zero.\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\therefore \\sum_{n=1}^{13}\\left(i^n+i^{n+1}\\right) & =\\left(i+i^2+\\ldots+i^{13}\\right) \\\\\n+ & \\left(i^2+i^3+\\ldots+i^{14}\\right)=i+i^2=i-1\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 278,
    "question": "The smallest positive integer $n$ for which $\\frac{1+i}{1-i}{ }^{n}=1$, is\\\\",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) 8\\\\",
        "b) 16\\\\",
        "c) 12\\\\",
        "d) None of these"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Since, $\\left(\\frac{1+i}{1-i}\\right)^n=1 \\Rightarrow\\left(\\frac{1+i}{1-i} \\times \\frac{1+i}{1+i}\\right)^n=1$\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\Rightarrow & & \\left(\\frac{2 i}{2}\\right)^n & =1 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow & i^n & =1\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nThe smallest positive integer $n$ for which $i^n=1$ is 4 .\n\n$$\n\\therefore \\quad n=4\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 280,
    "question": "The equation $|z-i|=|z-1|, i=\\sqrt{-1}$, represents",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) a circle of radius $\\frac{1}{2}$",
        "b) the line passing through the origin with slope 1",
        "c) a circle of radius 1",
        "d) the line passing through the origin with slope -1\\\\"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Let the complex number $z=x+i y$\n\nAlso given, $|z-i|=|z-1|$\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow|x+i y-i|=|x+i y-1|\n$$\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\sqrt{x^{2}+(y-1)^{2}}=\\sqrt{(x-1)^{2}+y^{2}}\n$$\n\n$$\n\\left[\\because|z|=\\sqrt{(\\operatorname{Re}(z))^{2}+(\\operatorname{Im}(z))^{2}}\\right]\n$$\n\nOn squaring both sides, we get\n\n$$\nx^{2}+y^{2}-2 y+1=x^{2}+y^{2}-2 x+1\n$$\n\n$\\Rightarrow y=x$, which represents a line through the origin with slope 1 .",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 27,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 281,
    "question": "If $a>0$ and $z=\\frac{(1+i)^{2}}{a-i}$, has magnitude $\\sqrt{\\frac{2}{5}}$, then $\\bar{z}$ is equal to",
    "reference": "2019 Main, 10 April I",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\frac{1}{5}-\\frac{3}{5} i$",
        "b) $-\\frac{1}{5}-\\frac{3}{5} i$",
        "c) $-\\frac{1}{5}+\\frac{3}{5} i$",
        "d) $-\\frac{3}{5}-\\frac{1}{5} i$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "The given complex number $z=\\frac{(1+i)^{2}}{a-i}$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\frac{(1-1+2 i)(a+i)}{a^{2}+1} \\\\\n& =\\frac{2 i(a+i)}{a^{2}+1}=\\frac{-2+2 a i}{a^{2}+1} \\\\\n& \\because \\quad|z|=\\sqrt{2 / 5} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad \\sqrt{\\frac{4+4 a^{2}}{\\left(a^{2}+1\\right)^{2}}}=\\sqrt{\\frac{2}{5}} \\Rightarrow \\frac{2}{\\sqrt{1+a^{2}}}=\\sqrt{\\frac{2}{5}} \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad \\frac{4}{1+a^{2}}=\\frac{2}{5} \\Rightarrow a^{2}+1=10 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad a^{2}=9 \\Rightarrow a=3 \\\\\n& {[\\because a>0] \\quad 1 \\quad} \\\\\n& \\therefore \\quad z=\\frac{-2+6 i}{10} \\\\\n& \\text { So, } \\bar{z}=\\frac{-2+6 i}{10}=-\\frac{1}{5}+\\frac{3}{5} i \\Rightarrow \\bar{z}=-\\frac{1}{5}-\\frac{3}{5} i \\\\\n& {[\\because \\text { if } z=x+i y \\text {, then } \\bar{z}=x-i y]}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 282,
    "question": "Let $z_{1}$ and $z_{2}$ be two complex numbers satisfying $\\left|z_{1}\\right|=9$ and $\\left|z_{2}-3-4 i\\right|=4$. Then, the minimum value of $\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right|$ is\\\\",
    "reference": "2019 Main, 12 Jan II",
    "options": [
        "a) 1\\\\",
        "b) 2\\\\",
        "c) $\\sqrt{2}$\\\\",
        "d) 0"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Clearly $\\left|z_{1}\\right|=9$, represents a circle having centre $C_{1}(0,0)$ and radius $r_{1}=9$.\n\nand $\\left|z_{2}-3-4 i\\right|=4$ represents a circle having centre $C_{2}(3,4)$ and radius $r_{2}=4$.\n\nThe minimum value of $\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right|$ is equals to minimum distance between circles $\\left|z_{1}\\right|=9$ and $\\left|z_{2}-3-4 i\\right|=4$.\n\n$\\because C_{1} C_{2}=\\sqrt{(3-0)^{2}+(4-0)^{2}}=\\sqrt{9+16}=\\sqrt{25}=5$\n\nand $\\left|r_{1}-r_{2}\\right| \\neq 9-4\\left|=5 \\Rightarrow C_{1} C_{2} \\# r_{1}-r_{2}\\right|$\n\n$\\therefore$ Circles touches each other internally.\n\nHence, $\\quad\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right|_{\\min }=0$\\\\",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 283,
    "question": "If $\\frac{z-\\alpha}{z+\\alpha}(\\alpha \\in R)$ is a purely imaginary number and $|z|=2$, then a value of $\\alpha$ is\\\\",
    "reference": "2019 Main, 12 Jan I",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\sqrt{2}$\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{1}{2}$\\\\",
        "c) 1\\\\",
        "d) 2"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Since, the complex number $\\frac{z-\\alpha}{z+\\alpha}(\\alpha \\in R)$ is purely imaginary number, therefore\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{rlr} \n& \\frac{z-\\alpha}{z+\\alpha}+\\frac{\\bar{z}-\\alpha}{\\bar{z}+\\alpha}=0 & {[\\because \\alpha \\in R]} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & z \\bar{z}-\\alpha \\bar{z}+\\alpha z-\\alpha^{2}+z \\bar{z}-\\alpha z+\\alpha \\bar{z}-\\alpha^{2}=0 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & 2|z|^{2}-2 \\alpha^{2}=0 & {\\left[\\because z \\bar{z}=|z|^{2}\\right]} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\alpha^{2}=|z|^{2}=4 & {[|z|=2 \\text { given }]} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\alpha= \\pm 2 &\n\\end{array}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 284,
    "question": "Let $z$ be a complex number such that $|z|+z=3+i$ (where $i=\\sqrt{-1}$ ).\n\nThen, $|z|$ is equal to\\\\",
    "reference": " 2019 Main, 11 Jan II",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\frac{\\sqrt{34}}{3}$\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{5}{3}$\\\\",
        "c) $\\frac{\\sqrt{41}}{4}$\\\\",
        "d) $\\frac{5}{4}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "We have, $|z|+z=3+i$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{lc}\n\\text { Let } & z=x+i y \\\\\n\\therefore & \\sqrt{x^{2}+y^{2}}+x+i y=3+i \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\left(x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+y^{2}}\\right)+i y=3+i \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & x+\\sqrt{x^{2}+y^{2}}=3 \\text { and } y=1 \\\\\n\\text { Now, } & \\sqrt{x^{2}+1}=3-x \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & x^{2}+1=9-6 x+x^{2} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & 6 x=8 \\Rightarrow x=\\frac{4}{3} \\\\\n\\therefore & z=\\frac{4}{3}+i \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & |z|=\\sqrt{\\frac{16}{9}+1}=\\sqrt{\\frac{25}{9}} \\Rightarrow|z|=\\frac{5}{3}\n\\end{array}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 285,
    "question": "A complex number $z$ is said to be unimodular, if $|z| \\neq 1$. If $z_{1}$ and $z_{2}$ are complex numbers such that $\\frac{z_{1}-2 z_{2}}{2-z_{1} \\bar{z}_{2}}$ is unimodular and $z_{2}$ is not unimodular.\n\nThen, the point $z_{1}$ lies on a",
    "reference": "2015 Main",
    "options": [
        "a) straight line parallel to $X$-axis",
        "b) straight line parallel to $Y$-axis",
        "c) circle of radius 2",
        "d) circle of radius $\\sqrt{2}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(c)",
    "solution": "PLAN If $z$ is unimodular, then $|z|=1$. Also, use property of modulus i.e. $z \\bar{z} \\neq\\left. z\\right|^{2}$\n\nGiven, $z_{2}$ is not unimodular i.e. $\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\neq 1$ and $\\frac{z_{1}-2 z_{2}}{2-z_{1} \\bar{z}_{2}}$ is unimodular.\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad\\left(z_{1}-3 z_{2}\\right)\\left(\\bar{z}_{1}-2 \\bar{z}_{2}\\right)=\\left(2-z_{1} \\bar{z}_{2}\\right)\\left(2-\\bar{z}_{1} z_{2}\\right) \\quad\\left[z \\bar{z}=|z|^{2}\\right] \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow\\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}+4\\left|z_{2}\\right|^{2}-2 \\bar{z}_{1} z_{2}-2 z_{1} \\bar{z}_{2} \\\\\n& \\quad=4+\\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}\\left|z_{2}\\right|^{2}-2 \\bar{z}_{1} z_{2}-2 z_{1} \\bar{z}_{2} \\Rightarrow\\left(\\left|z_{2}\\right|^{2}-1\\right)\\left(\\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}-4\\right)=0 \\\\\n& \\because \\quad\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\neq 1 \\\\\n& \\therefore \\quad\\left|z_{1}\\right|=2 \\\\\n& \\text { Let } \\quad z_{1}=x+i y \\Rightarrow x^{2}+y^{2}=(2)^{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\n$\\therefore \\quad$ Point $z_{1}$ lies on a circle of radius 2 .",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 286,
    "question": "If $z$ is a complex number such that $|z| \\geq 2$, then the minimum value of $\\left|z+\\frac{1}{2}\\right|$",
    "reference": "2014 Main",
    "options": [
        "a) is equal to $5 / 2$",
        "b) lies in the interval $(1,2)$",
        "c) is strictly greater than $5 / 2$",
        "d) is strictly greater than $3 / 2$ but less than $5 / 2$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "$|z| \\geq 2$ is the region on or outside circle whose centre is $(0,0)$ and radius is 2 .\n\nMinimum $\\left|z+\\frac{1}{2}\\right|$ is distance of $z$, which lie on circle $|z|=2$ from $(-1 / 2,0)$.\n\n$\\therefore$ Minimum $\\left|z+\\frac{1}{2}\\right|=$ Distance of $-\\frac{1}{2}, 0$ from $(-2,0)$\n\n$$\n=\\sqrt{-2+\\frac{1}{2}^{2}+0}=\\frac{3}{2}=\\sqrt{\\frac{-1}{2}+2^{2}+0}=\\frac{3}{2}\n$$\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-11}\n\\end{center}\n\nGeometrically Min $\\left|z+\\frac{1}{2}\\right|=A D$ Hence, minimum value of $\\left|z+\\frac{1}{2}\\right|$ lies in the interval\\\\\n$(1,2)$.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 287,
    "question": "Let complex numbers $\\alpha$ and $1 / \\bar{\\alpha}$ lies on circles $\\left(x-x_{0}\\right)^{2}+\\left(y-y_{0}\\right)^{2}=r^{2}$ and $\\left(x-x_{0}\\right)^{2}+\\left(y-y_{0}\\right)^{2}=4 r^{2}$, respectively.\n\nIf $z_{0}=x_{0}+i y_{0}$ satisfies the equation $2\\left|z_{0}\\right|^{2}=r^{2}+2$, then $|\\alpha|$ is equal to\\\\",
    "reference": "2013 Adv.",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}$\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{1}{2}$\\\\",
        "c) $\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{7}}$\\\\",
        "d) $\\frac{1}{3}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(c)",
    "solution": "PLAN Intersection of circles, the basic concept is to solve the equations simultaneously and using properties of modulus of complex numbers\n\nFormula used $\\quad|z|^{2}=z \\cdot \\bar{z}$\n\nand\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right|^{2} & =\\left(z_{1}-z_{2}\\right)\\left(\\bar{z}_{1}-\\bar{z}_{2}\\right) \\\\\n& =\\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}-z_{1} \\bar{z}_{2}-z_{2} \\bar{z}_{1}+\\left|z_{2}\\right|^{2}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nHere, $\\left(x-x_{0}\\right)^{2}+\\left(y-y_{0}\\right)^{2}=r^{2}$\n\nand $\\left(x-x_{0}\\right)^{2}+\\left(y-y_{0}\\right)^{2}=4 r^{2}$ can be written as,\n\n$$\n\\left|z-z_{0}\\right|^{2}=r^{2} \\text { and }\\left|z-z_{0}\\right|^{2}=4 r^{2}\n$$\n\nSince, $\\alpha$ and $\\frac{1}{\\bar{\\alpha}}$ lies on first and second respectively.\n\n\\[\n\\begin{array}{rlrl} \n& \\left|\\alpha-z_{0}\\right|^{2} & =r^{2} \\text { and }\\left|\\frac{1}{\\bar{\\alpha}}-z_{0}\\right|^{2}=4 r^{2} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\left(\\alpha-z_{0}\\right)\\left(\\bar{\\alpha}-\\bar{z}_{0}\\right) & =r^{2} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow \\quad|\\alpha|^{2}-z_{0} \\bar{\\alpha}-\\bar{z}_{0} \\alpha+\\left|z_{0}\\right|^{2} & =r^{2} \\tag{i}\n\\end{array}\n\\]\n\nand $\\quad\\left|\\frac{1}{\\bar{\\alpha}}-z_{0}\\right|^{2}=4 r^{2}$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{lr}\n\\Rightarrow & \\frac{1}{\\bar{\\alpha}}-z_{0} \\quad \\frac{1}{\\alpha}-\\bar{z}_{0}=4 r^{2} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\frac{1}{|\\alpha|^{2}}-\\frac{z_{0}}{\\alpha}-\\frac{\\bar{z}_{0}}{\\bar{\\alpha}}+\\left|z_{0}\\right|^{2}=4 r^{2}\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\nSince,\n\n$$\n|\\alpha|^{2}=\\alpha \\cdot \\alpha\n$$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\frac{1}{|\\alpha|^{2}}-\\frac{z_{0} \\cdot \\bar{\\alpha}}{|\\alpha|^{2}}-\\frac{\\bar{z}_{0}}{|\\alpha|^{2}} \\cdot \\alpha+\\left|z_{0}\\right|^{2}=4 r^{2}$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad 1-z_{0} \\bar{\\alpha}-\\bar{z}_{0} \\alpha+|\\alpha|^{2}\\left|z_{0}\\right|^{2}=4 r^{2}|\\alpha|^{2}$\n\nOn subtracting Eqs. (i) and (ii), we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\quad\\left(|\\alpha|^{2}-1\\right)+\\left|z_{0}\\right|^{2}\\left(1-|\\alpha|^{2}\\right)=r^{2}\\left(1-4|\\alpha|^{2}\\right) \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad\\left(|\\alpha|^{2}-1\\right)\\left(1-\\left|z_{0}\\right|^{2}\\right)=r^{2}\\left(1-4|\\alpha|^{2}\\right) \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad\\left(|\\alpha|^{2}-1\\right) 1-\\frac{r^{2}+2}{2}=r^{2}\\left(1-4|\\alpha|^{2}\\right) \\\\\n& \\text { Given, }\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\Rightarrow & \\left(|\\alpha|^{2}-1\\right) \\cdot \\frac{r^{2}}{2} & =r^{2}\\left(1-4|\\alpha|^{2}\\right) \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & |\\alpha|^{2}-1 & =-2+8|\\alpha|^{2} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & 7|\\alpha|^{2} & =1 \\\\\n\\therefore & |\\alpha| & =1 / \\sqrt{7}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 288,
    "question": "Let $z$ be a complex number such that the imaginary part of $z$ is non-zero and $a=z^{2}+z+1$ is real. Then, $a$ cannot take the value\\\\",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) -1\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{1}{3}$\\\\",
        "c) $\\frac{1}{2}$\\\\",
        "d) $\\frac{3}{4}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "PLAN If $a x^{2}+b x+c=0$ has roots $\\alpha, \\beta$, then\n\n$$\n\\alpha, \\beta=\\frac{-b \\pm \\sqrt{b^{2}-4 a c}}{2 a}\n$$\n\nFor roots to be real $b^{2}-4 a c \\geq 0$.\n\nDescription of Situation As imaginary part of $z=x+i y$ is non-zero.\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad y \\neq 0$\n\nMethod I Let $z=x+i y$\n\n\\[\n\\begin{array}{lc}\n\\therefore & a=(x+i y)^{2}+(x+i y)+1 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\left(x^{2}-y^{2}+x+1-a\\right)+i(2 x y+y)=0 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\left(x^{2}-y^{2}+x+1-a\\right)+i y(2 x+1)=0 \\tag{i}\n\\end{array}\n\\]\n\nIt is purely real, if $y(2 x+1)=0$\n\nbut imaginary part of $z$, i.e. $y$ is non-zero.\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\quad 2 x+1=0 \\text { or } x=-1 / 2\n$$\n\nFrom Eq. (i), $\\frac{1}{4}-y^{2}-\\frac{1}{2}+1-a=0$\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\quad a=-y^{2}+\\frac{3}{4} \\Rightarrow a<\\frac{3}{4}\n$$\n\nMethod II Here, $z^{2}+z+(1-a)=0$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{ll}\n\\therefore & z=\\frac{-1 \\pm \\sqrt{1-4(1-a)}}{2 \\times 1} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & z=\\frac{-1 \\pm \\sqrt{4 a-3}}{2}\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\nFor $z$ do not have real roots, $4 a-3<0 \\Rightarrow a<\\frac{3}{4}$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 289,
    "question": "Let $z=x+i y$ be a complex number where, $x$ and $y$ are integers. Then, the area of the rectangle whose vertices are the root of the equation $z \\bar{z}^{3}+\\bar{z} z^{3}=350$, is\\\\",
    "reference": "2009",
    "options": [
        "a) 48\\\\",
        "b) 32\\\\",
        "c) 40\\\\",
        "d) 80"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(a)",
    "solution": "Since,\n\n$$\nz \\bar{z}\\left(z^{2}+\\bar{z}^{2}\\right)=350\n$$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad 2\\left(x^{2}+y^{2}\\right)\\left(x^{2}-y^{2}\\right)=350$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad\\left(x^{2}+y^{2}\\right)\\left(x^{2}-y^{2}\\right)=175$\n\nSince, $x, y \\in I$, the only possible case which gives integral solution, is\n\n\n\\begin{align*}\n& x^{2}+y^{2}=25  \\tag{i}\\\\\n& x^{2}-y^{2}=7 \\tag{ii}\n\\end{align*}\n\n\nFrom Eqs. (i) and (ii),\n\n$$\nx^{2}=16, y^{2}=9 \\Rightarrow x= \\pm 4, y= \\pm 3\n$$\n\n$\\therefore$ Area of rectangle $=8 \\times 6=48$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 290,
    "question": "If $|z|=1$ and $z \\neq \\pm 1$, then all the values of $\\frac{z}{1-z^{2}}$ lie on",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) a line not passing through the origin",
        "b) $|z|=\\sqrt{2}$",
        "c) the $X$-axis",
        "d) the $Y$-axis\\\\"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Let $z=\\cos \\theta+i \\sin \\theta$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\Rightarrow \\quad \\frac{z}{1-z^{2}} & =\\frac{\\cos \\theta+i \\sin \\theta}{1-(\\cos 2 \\theta+i \\sin 2 \\theta)} \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\cos \\theta+i \\sin \\theta}{2 \\sin ^{2} \\theta-2 i \\sin \\theta \\cos \\theta} \\\\\n& =\\frac{\\cos \\theta+i \\sin \\theta}{-2 i \\sin \\theta(\\cos \\theta+i \\sin \\theta)}=\\frac{i}{2 \\sin \\theta}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nHence, $\\frac{z}{1-z^{2}}$ lies on the imaginary axis i.e. $Y$-axis.\n\n\\section*{12 Complex Numbers}\n\\section*{Alternate Solution}\nLet $E=\\frac{z}{1-z^{2}}=\\frac{z}{z \\bar{z}-z^{2}}=\\frac{1}{\\bar{z}-z}$ which is an imaginary.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 28,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 291,
    "question": "If $w=\\alpha+i \\beta$, where $\\beta \\neq 0$ and $z \\neq 1$, satisfies the condition that $\\frac{w-\\bar{w} z}{1-z}$ is purely real, then the set of values of $z$ is\\\\",
    "reference": "2006, 3M",
    "options": [
        "a) $|z|=1, z \\neq 2$\\\\",
        "b) $|z|=1$ and $z \\neq 1$\\\\",
        "c) $z=\\bar{z}$\\\\",
        "d) None of these"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Let $z_{1}=\\frac{w-\\bar{w} z}{1-z}$ be purely real $\\Rightarrow \\quad z_{1}=\\bar{z}_{1}$\n\n$\\therefore \\quad \\frac{w-\\bar{w} z}{1-z}=\\frac{\\bar{w}-w \\bar{z}}{1-\\bar{z}}$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad w-w \\bar{z}-\\bar{w} z+\\bar{w} z \\cdot \\bar{z}=\\bar{w}-z \\bar{w}-w \\bar{z}+w z \\cdot \\bar{z}$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad(w-\\bar{w})+(\\bar{w}-w)|z|^{2}=0$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad(w-\\bar{w})\\left(1-|z|^{2}\\right)=0$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad|z|^{2}=1 \\quad$ as $w-\\bar{w} \\neq 0$, since $\\beta \\neq 0$ ]\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad|z|=1$ and $z \\neq 1$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 292,
    "question": "If $|z|=1$ and $w=\\frac{z-1}{z+1}$ (where, $z \\neq-1$ ), then $\\operatorname{Re}(w)$ is",
    "reference": "2003, 1M",
    "options": [
        "a) 0\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{1}{|z+1|^{2}}$\\\\",
        "c) $\\frac{1}{z+1} \\cdot \\frac{1}{|z+1|^{2}}$\\\\",
        "d) $\\frac{\\sqrt{2}}{|z+1|^{2}}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(a)",
    "solution": "Since, $|z|=1$ and $w=\\frac{z-1}{z+1}$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{lll}\n\\Rightarrow & z-1=w z+w \\Rightarrow z=\\frac{1+w}{1-w} \\Rightarrow & |z|=\\frac{|1+w|}{|1-w|} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & |1-w|=|1+w| & {[\\because|z|=1]}\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\nOn squaring both sides, we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{cc} \n& 1+|w|^{2}-2|w| \\operatorname{Re}(w)=1+|w|^{2}+2|w| \\operatorname{Re}(w) \\\\\n& {\\left[\\text { using }\\left|z_{1} \\pm z_{2}\\right|^{2}=\\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}+\\left|z_{2}\\right|^{2} \\pm 2\\left|z_{1}\\right|\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\operatorname{Re}\\left(\\bar{z}_{1} z_{2}\\right)\\right]} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & 4|w| \\operatorname{Re}|w|=0 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\operatorname{Re}(w)=0\n\\end{array}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 293,
    "question": "For all complex numbers $z_{1}, z_{2}$ satisfying $\\left|z_{1}\\right|=12$ and $\\left|z_{2}-3-4 i\\right|=5$, the minimum value of $\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right|$ is\\\\",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) 0\\\\",
        "b) 2\\\\",
        "c) 7\\\\",
        "d) 17"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "We know, $\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right|=\\left|z_{1}-\\left(z_{2}-3-4 i\\right)-(3+4 i)\\right|$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\geq\\left|z_{1}\\right|-\\left|z_{2}-3-4 i\\right|-|3+4 i| \\\\\n& \\geq 12-5-5 \\quad\\left[\\text { using }\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right| \\geq\\left|z_{1}\\right|-\\left|z_{2}\\right|\\right]\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\n$$\n\\therefore \\quad\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right| \\geq 2\n$$\n\n\\section*{Alternate Solution}\nClearly from the figure $\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right|$ is minimum when $z_{1}, z_{2}$ lie along the diameter.\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-12}\n\\end{center}\n\n$\\therefore \\quad\\left|z_{1}-z_{2}\\right| \\geq C_{2} B-C_{2} A \\geq 12-10=2$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 294,
    "question": "If $z_{1}, z_{2}$ and $z_{3}$ are complex numbers such that $\\left|z_{1}\\right|=\\left|z_{2}\\right|=\\left|z_{3}\\right|=\\frac{1}{z_{1}}+\\frac{1}{z_{2}}+\\frac{1}{z_{3}}=1$, then $\\left|z_{1}+z_{2}+z_{3}\\right|$ is\\\\",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) equal to 1\\\\",
        "b) less than 1\\\\",
        "c) greater than 3\\\\",
        "d) equal to 3"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(a)",
    "solution": "Given,\n\n$$\n\\left|z_{1}\\right|=\\left|z_{2}\\right|=\\left|z_{3}\\right|=1\n$$\n\nNow,\n\n$$\n\\left|z_{1}\\right|=1\n$$\n\n$\\Rightarrow$\n\n$$\n\\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}=1 \\Rightarrow z_{1} \\bar{z}_{1}=1\n$$\n\nSimilarly,\n\n$$\nz_{2} \\bar{z}_{2}=1, z_{3} \\bar{z}_{3}=1\n$$\n\nAgain now,\n\n$$\n\\frac{1}{z_{1}}+\\frac{1}{z_{2}}+\\frac{1}{z_{3}}=1\n$$\n\n$\\Rightarrow\\left|\\bar{z}_{1}+\\bar{z}_{2}+\\bar{z}_{3}\\right|=1 \\Rightarrow \\overline{\\left|z_{1}+z_{2}+z_{3}\\right|}=1$\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\quad\\left|z_{1}+z_{2}+z_{3}\\right|=1\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 295,
    "question": "For positive integers $n_{1}, n_{2}$ the value of expression $(1+i)^{n_{1}}+\\left(1+i^{3}\\right)^{n_{1}}+\\left(1+i^{5}\\right)^{n_{2}}+\\left(1+i^{7}\\right)^{n_{2}}$, here $i=\\sqrt{-1}$ is a real number, if and only if\\\\",
    "reference": "1996, 2M",
    "options": [
        "a) $n_{1}=n_{2}+1$\\\\",
        "b) $n_{1}=n_{2}-1$\\\\",
        "c) $n_{1}=n_{2}$\\\\",
        "d) $n_{1}>0, n_{2}>0$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "$(1+i)^{n_{1}}+(1-i)^{n_{1}}+(1+i)^{n_{2}}+(1-i)^{n_{2}}$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& =\\left[{ }^{n_{1}} C_{0}+{ }^{n_{1}} C_{1} i+{ }^{n_{1}} C_{2} i^{2}+{ }^{n_{1}} C_{3} i^{3}+\\ldots\\right] \\\\\n& \\quad+\\left[\\left[^{n_{1}} C_{0}-{ }^{n_{1}} C_{1} i+{ }^{n_{1}} C_{2} i^{2}-{ }^{n_{1}} C_{3} i^{3}+\\ldots\\right]\\right. \\\\\n& \\quad+\\left[{ }^{n_{2}} C_{0}+{ }^{n_{2}} C_{1} i+{ }^{n_{2}} C_{2} i^{2}+{ }^{n_{2}} C_{3} i^{3}+\\ldots\\right] \\\\\n& \\quad+\\left[{ }^{n_{2}} C_{0}-{ }^{n_{2}} C_{1} i+{ }^{n_{2}} C_{2} i^{2}-{ }^{n_{2}} C_{3} i^{3}+. .\\right] \\\\\n& =2\\left[{ }^{n_{1}} C_{0}+{ }^{n_{1}} C_{2} i^{2}+{ }^{n_{1}} C_{4} i^{4}+\\ldots\\right] \\\\\n& \\quad+2\\left[{ }^{n_{2}} C_{0}+{ }^{n_{2}} C_{2} i^{2}+{ }^{n_{2}} C_{4} i^{4}+\\ldots\\right] \\\\\n& =2\\left[{ }^{n_{1}} C_{0}-{ }^{n_{1}} C_{2}+{ }^{n_{1}} C_{4}-\\ldots\\right]+2\\left[{ }^{n_{2}} C_{0}-{ }^{n_{2}} C_{2}\\right. \\\\\n& \\left.\\quad+{ }^{n_{2}} C_{4}-\\ldots\\right]\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nThis is a real number irrespective of the values of $n_{1}$ and $n_{2}$.\n\n\\section*{Alternate Solution}\n$$\n\\left\\{(1+i)^{n_{1}}+(1-i)^{n_{1}}\\right\\}+\\left\\{(1+i)^{n_{2}}+(1-i)^{n_{2}}\\right\\}\n$$\n\n$\\Rightarrow$ A real number for all $n_{1}$ and $n_{2} \\in R$.\n\n$\\left[\\because z+\\bar{z}=2 \\operatorname{Re}(z) \\Rightarrow(1+i)^{n_{1}}+(1-i)^{n_{1}}\\right.$ is real number for all $n \\in R]$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 296,
    "question": "The complex numbers $\\sin x+i \\cos 2 x$ and $\\cos x-i \\sin 2 x$ are conjugate to each other, for\\\\",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) $x=n \\pi$\\\\",
        "b) $x=0$\\\\",
        "c) $x=(n+1 / 2) \\pi$\\\\",
        "d) no value of $x$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Since, $(\\overline{\\sin x+i \\cos 2 x})=\\cos x-i \\sin 2 x$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad \\sin x-i \\cos 2 x=\\cos x-i \\sin 2 x$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad \\sin x=\\cos x$ and $\\cos 2 x=\\sin 2 x$\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad \\tan x=1$ and $\\tan 2 x=1$\n\n$\\Rightarrow x=\\pi / 4$ and $x=\\pi / 8$ which is not possible at same time.\n\nHence, no solution exists.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 297,
    "question": "The points $z_{1}, z_{2}, z_{3}$ and $z_{4}$ in the complex plane are the vertices of a parallelogram taken in order, if and only if\\\\",
    "reference": " ",
    "options": [
        "a) $z_{1}+z_{4}=z_{2}+z_{3}$\\\\",
        "b) $z_{1}+z_{3}=z_{2}+z_{4}$\\\\",
        "c) $z_{1}+z_{2}=z_{3}+z_{4}$\\\\",
        "d) None of these"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Since, $z_{1}, z_{2}, z_{3}, z_{4}$ are the vertices of parallelogram.\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-12(1)}\n\\end{center}\n\n$\\therefore$ Mid-point of $A C=$ mid-point of $B D$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{ll}\n\\Rightarrow & \\frac{z_{1}+z_{3}}{2}=\\frac{z_{2}+z_{4}}{2} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & z_{1}+z_{3}=z_{2}+z_{4}\n\\end{array}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 298,
    "question": "If $z=x+i y$ and $w=(1-i z) /(z-i)$, then $|w|=1$ implies that, in the complex plane\\\\",
    "reference": "1983, 1M",
    "options": [
        "a) $z$ lies on the imaginary axis\\\\",
        "b) $z$ lies on the real axis\\\\",
        "c) $z$ lies on the unit circle\\\\",
        "d) None of these"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Since, $|w|=1 \\Rightarrow \\frac{1-i z}{z-i}=1$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{llrl}\n\\Rightarrow & |z-i|=|1-i z| \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & |z-i|=|z+i| & {[\\because|1-i z|=|-i||z+i|=|z+i|]}\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\n$\\therefore$ It is a perpendicular bisector of $(0,1)$ and $(0,-1)$\n\ni.e. $X$-axis. Thus, $z$ lies on the real axis.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 299,
    "question": "The inequality $|z-4|<|z-2|$ represents the region given by\\\\",
    "reference": "1982, 2M",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\operatorname{Re}(z) \\geq 0$\\\\",
        "b) $\\operatorname{Re}(z)<0$\\\\",
        "c) $\\operatorname{Re}(z)>0$\\\\",
        "d) None of these"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Given, $|z-4|<|z-2|$\n\nSince, $\\left|z-z_{1}\\right|>\\left|z-z_{2}\\right|$ represents the region on right side of perpendicular bisector of $z_{1}$ and $z_{2}$.\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{ll}\n\\therefore & |z-2|>|z-4| \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & \\operatorname{Re}(z)>3 \\quad \\text { and } \\operatorname{Im}(z) \\in R\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-13(2)}\n\\end{center}",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 300,
    "question": "If $z=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}+\\frac{i}{2}^{5}+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}-\\frac{i}{2}^{5}$, then\\\\",
    "reference": "1982, 2M",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\operatorname{Re}(z)=0$\\\\",
        "b) $\\operatorname{Im}(z)=0$\\\\",
        "c) $\\operatorname{Re}(z)>0, \\operatorname{Im}(z)>0$\\\\",
        "d) $\\operatorname{Re}(z)>0, \\operatorname{Im}(z)<0$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Given, $z=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}+\\frac{i}{2}^{5}+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}-\\frac{i}{2}^{5}$\n\n$$\n\\because \\omega=\\frac{-1+i \\sqrt{3}}{2} \\text { and } \\omega^{2}=\\frac{-1-i \\sqrt{3}}{2}\n$$\n\nNow, $\\quad \\frac{\\sqrt{3}+i}{2}=-i \\frac{-1+i \\sqrt{3}}{2}=-i \\omega$\n\nand $\\quad \\frac{\\sqrt{3}-i}{2}=i \\frac{-1-i \\sqrt{3}}{2}=i \\omega^{2}$\n\n$$\n\\therefore \\quad z=(-i \\omega)^{5}+\\left(i \\omega^{2}\\right)^{5}=-i \\omega^{2}+i \\omega\n$$\n\n$$\n=i\\left(\\omega-\\omega^{2}\\right)=i(i \\sqrt{3})=-\\sqrt{3}\n$$\n\n$$\n\\Rightarrow \\quad \\operatorname{Re}(z)<0 \\text { and } \\operatorname{lm}(z)=0\n$$\n\n\\section*{Alternate Solution}\nWe know that, $\\quad z+\\bar{z}=2 \\operatorname{Re}(z)$\n\nIf\n\n$$\nz=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}+\\frac{i}{2}+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}-\\frac{i}{2}^{5}, \\text { then }\n$$\n\n$z$ is purely real. i.e. $\\operatorname{Im}(z)=0$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 29,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 301,
    "question": "The complex numbers $z=x+i y$ which satisfy the equation $\\frac{z-5 i}{z+5 i}=1$, lie on",
    "reference": "1981, 2M",
    "options": [
        "a) the $X$-axis",
        "b) the straight line $y=5$",
        "c) a circle passing through the origin",
        "d) None of the above"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(a)",
    "solution": "Given, $\\frac{z-5 i}{z+5 i}=1 \\Rightarrow|z-5 i|=|z+5 i|$\n\n$\\left[\\because\\right.$ if $\\left|z-z_{1}\\right|=\\left|z-z_{2}\\right|$, then it is a perpendicular\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth, center]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-13}\\\\\n\\end{center}\nbisector of $z_{1}$ and $z_{2}$ ]\n\n$\\therefore$ Perpendicular bisector of $(0,5)$ and $(0,-5)$ is $X$-axis.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 327,
    "question": "If $z$ is any complex number satisfying $|z-3-2 i| \\leq 2$, then the maximum value of $|2 z-6+5 i|$ is ",
    "reference": " (2011)",
    "options": [],
    "question_type": "Integer Answer Type Question",
    "answer": "5",
    "solution": "Given, $|z-3-2 i| \\leq 2$\n\nTo find minimum of $|2 z-6+5 i|$\n\nor $2\\left|z-3+\\frac{5}{2} i\\right|$, using triangle inequality\n\ni.e. ||$z_{1}|-| z_{2}|| \\leq\\left|z_{1}+z_{2}\\right|$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{rlrl}\n\\therefore & & \\left|z-3+\\frac{5}{2} i\\right| & =\\left|z-3-2 i+2 i+\\frac{5}{2} i\\right| \\\\\n& =\\left|(z-3-2 i)+\\frac{9}{2} i\\right| \\\\\n& & \\geq|| z-3-2 i\\left|-\\frac{9}{2}\\right| \\geq\\left|2-\\frac{9}{2}\\right| \\geq \\frac{5}{2} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & & \\left|z-3+\\frac{5}{2} i\\right| \\geq \\frac{5}{2} \\text { or }|2 z-6+5 i| \\geq 5\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\n\\section*{Topic 3 Argument of a Complex Number}",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 328,
    "question": "Let $z_{1}$ and $z_{2}$ be any two non-zero complex numbers such that $3\\left|z_{1}\\right|=4\\left|z_{2}\\right|$. If $z=\\frac{3 z_{1}}{2 z_{2}}+\\frac{2 z_{2}}{3 z_{1}}$, then\\\\",
    "reference": "\n\n(2019 Main, 10 Jan I) ",
    "options": [
        "a) $|z|=\\frac{1}{2} \\sqrt{\\frac{17}{2}}$\\\\",
        "b) $\\operatorname{Im}(z)=0$\\\\",
        "c) $\\operatorname{Re}(z)=0$\\\\",
        "d) $|z|=\\sqrt{\\frac{5}{2}}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(None)",
    "solution": "(*) Given, $3\\left|z_{1}\\right|=4\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\Rightarrow \\frac{\\left|z_{1}\\right|}{\\left|z_{2}\\right|}=\\frac{4}{3} \\quad\\left[\\because z_{2} \\neq 0 \\Rightarrow\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\neq 0\\right]$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\therefore \\quad \\frac{z_{1}}{z_{2}}=\\left|\\frac{z_{1}}{z_{2}}\\right| e^{i \\theta} \\text { and } \\frac{z_{2}}{z_{1}}=\\left|\\frac{z_{2}}{z_{1}}\\right| e^{-i \\theta} \\\\\n& \\left.\\Rightarrow \\frac{z_{1}}{z_{2}}=\\frac{4}{3} e^{i \\theta} \\text { and } \\frac{z_{2}}{z_{1}}=|z|(\\cos \\theta+i \\sin \\theta)=|z| e^{i \\theta}\\right] \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad \\frac{3}{2} \\frac{z_{1}}{z_{2}}=2 e^{i \\theta} \\text { and } \\frac{2}{3} \\frac{z_{2}}{z_{1}}=\\frac{1}{2} e^{-i \\theta}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nOn adding these two, we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& z=\\frac{3}{2} \\frac{z_{1}}{z_{2}}+\\frac{2}{3} \\frac{z_{2}}{z_{1}}=2 e^{i \\theta}+\\frac{1}{2} e^{-i \\theta} \\\\\n&= 2 \\cos \\theta+2 i \\sin \\theta+\\frac{1}{2} \\cos \\theta-\\frac{1}{2} i \\sin \\theta \\\\\n& \\quad\\left[\\because e^{ \\pm i \\theta}=(\\cos \\theta \\pm i \\sin \\theta)\\right] \\\\\n&= \\frac{5}{2} \\cos \\theta+\\frac{3}{2} i \\sin \\theta \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad|z|=\\sqrt{\\frac{5}{2}^{2}+\\frac{3}{2}^{2}}=\\sqrt{\\frac{34}{4}}=\\sqrt{\\frac{17}{2}}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nNote that $z$ is neither purely imaginary and nor purely real.\n\n(*) None of the options is correct.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 329,
    "question": "If $z$ is a complex number of unit modulus and argument $\\theta$, then arg $\\frac{1+z}{1+\\bar{z}}$ is equal to\\\\",
    "reference": "2013 Main",
    "options": [
        "a) $-\\theta$\\\\",
        "b) $\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\theta$\\\\",
        "c) $\\theta$\\\\",
        "d) $\\pi-\\theta$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(c)",
    "solution": "Given, $|z|=1, \\arg z=\\theta \\therefore z=e^{i \\theta}$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\therefore \\quad \\bar{z}=e^{-i \\theta} \\Rightarrow \\bar{z}=\\frac{1}{z} \\\\\n& \\therefore \\quad \\arg \\quad \\frac{1+z}{1+\\bar{z}}=\\arg \\frac{1+z}{1+\\frac{1}{z}}=\\arg (z)=\\theta\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 330,
    "question": "If $\\arg (z)<0$, then $\\arg (-z)-\\arg (z)$ equals \\\\",
    "reference": " (2000,2 M)",
    "options": [
        "a) $\\pi$\\\\",
        "b) $-\\pi$\\\\",
        "c) $-\\pi / 2$\\\\",
        "d) $\\pi / 2$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(a)",
    "solution": "Since, $\\arg (z)<0 \\Rightarrow \\quad \\arg (z)=-\\theta$\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-18}\n\\end{center}\n\n$\\Rightarrow \\quad z=r \\cos (-\\theta)+i \\sin (-\\theta)$\n\n$$\n=r(\\cos \\theta-i \\sin \\theta)\n$$\n\nand $\\quad-z=-r[\\cos \\theta-i \\sin \\theta]$\n\n$$\n=r[\\cos (\\pi-\\theta)+i \\sin (\\pi-\\theta)]\n$$\n\n$$\n\\therefore \\quad \\arg (-z)=\\pi-\\theta\n$$\n\nThus, $\\arg (-z)-\\arg (z)$\n\n$$\n=\\pi-\\theta-(-\\theta)=\\pi\n$$\n\n\\section*{Alternate Solution}\nReason $\\arg (-z)-\\arg z=\\arg \\frac{-z}{z}=\\arg (-1)=\\pi$ and also $\\arg z-\\arg (-z)=\\arg \\frac{z}{-z}=\\arg (-1)=\\pi$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 331,
    "question": "Let $z$ and $w$ be two complex numbers such that $|z| \\leq 1$, $|w| \\leq 1$ and $|z+i w|=|z-i \\bar{w}|=2$, then $z$ equals\n\\\\",
    "reference": "\n\n(1995, 2M) ",
    "options": [
        "a) 1 or $i$\\\\",
        "b) $i$ or $-i$\\\\",
        "c) 1 or -1\\\\",
        "d) $i$ or -1"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(c)",
    "solution": "Given,\n\n$$\n|z+i w|=|z-i \\bar{w}|=2\n$$\n\n$\\Rightarrow$\n\n$\\Rightarrow$\n\n$\\therefore z$ lies on the perpendicular bisector of the line joining $-i w$ and $-i \\bar{w}$. Since, $-i \\bar{w}$ is the mirror image of $-i w$ in the $X$-axis, the locus of $z$ is the $X$-axis.\n\nLet $\\quad z=x+i y$ and $y=0$.\n\nNow, $\\quad|z| \\leq 1 \\Rightarrow x^{2}+0^{2} \\leq 1 \\Rightarrow-1 \\leq x \\leq 1$.\n\n$\\therefore z$ may take values given in option (c).\n\n\\section*{Alternate Solution}\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& |z+i w| \\leq|z|+|i w|=|z|+|w| \\\\\n& \\leq 1+1=2 \\\\\n& \\therefore \\quad|z+i w| \\leq 2 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad|z+i w|=2 \\text { holds when } \\\\\n& \\arg z-\\arg i w=0 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad \\arg \\frac{z}{i w}=0\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nSimilarly, when $|z-i \\bar{w}|=2$, then $\\frac{z}{\\bar{w}}$ is purely imaginary\n\nNow, given relation\n\n$$\n|z+i w|=|z-i \\bar{w}|=2\n$$\n\nPut $w=i$, we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\left|z+i^{2}\\right|=\\left|z+i^{2}\\right|=2 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad|z-1|=2 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad z=-1 \\quad[\\because|z| \\leq 1]\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n\nPut $w=-i$, we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad\\left|z-i^{2}\\right|=\\left|z-i^{2}\\right|=2 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad|z+1|=2 \\Rightarrow \\quad z=1 \\\\\n& \\therefore \\quad z=1 \\text { or }-1 \\text { is the correct option. }\n\\end{aligned} \\quad[\\because|z| \\leq 1]\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 332,
    "question": "Let $z$ and $w$ be two non-zero complex numbers such that $|z|=|w|$ and $\\arg (z)+\\arg (w)=\\pi$, then $z$ equals\\\\",
    "reference": "\n\n(1995, 2M) ",
    "options": [
        "a) $w$\\\\",
        "b) $-w$\\\\",
        "c) $\\bar{w}$\\\\",
        "d) $-\\bar{w}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Since, $|z|=|w|$ and $\\arg (z)=\\pi-\\arg (w)$\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\text { Let } & w & =r e e^{i \\theta}, \\text { then } \\bar{w}=r e \\\\\n\\therefore & & z=r e^{i(\\pi-\\theta)}=r e^{i \\pi} \\cdot e^{-i \\theta}=-r e^{-i \\theta}=-\\bar{w}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 333,
    "question": "If $z_{1}$ and $z_{2}$ are two non-zero complex numbers such that $\\left|z_{1}+z_{2}\\right|=\\left|z_{1}\\right|+\\left|z_{2}\\right|$, then $\\arg \\left(z_{1}\\right)-\\arg \\left(z_{2}\\right)$ is equal to\\\\",
    "reference": "\n\n(1987, 2M) ",
    "options": [
        "a) $-\\pi$\\\\",
        "b) $-\\frac{\\pi}{2}$\\\\",
        "c) 0\\\\",
        "d) $\\frac{\\pi}{2}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(c)",
    "solution": "Given, $\\left|z_{1}+z_{2}\\right|=\\left|z_{1}\\right|+\\left|z_{2}\\right|$\n\nOn squaring both sides, we get\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}+\\left|z_{2}\\right|^{2}+2\\left|z_{1}\\right|\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\cos \\left(\\arg z_{1}-\\arg z_{2}\\right) \\\\\n& =\\left|z_{1}\\right|^{2}+\\left|z_{2}\\right|^{2}+2\\left|z_{1}\\right|\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad 2\\left|z_{1}\\right|\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\cos \\left(\\arg z_{1}-\\arg z_{2}\\right)=2\\left|z_{1}\\right|\\left|z_{2}\\right| \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad \\cos \\left(\\arg z_{1}-\\arg z_{2}\\right)=1 \\\\\n& \\Rightarrow \\quad \\arg \\left(z_{1}\\right)-\\arg \\left(z_{2}\\right)=0\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 334,
    "question": "If $a, b, c$ and $u, v, w$ are the complex numbers representing the vertices of two triangles such that $c=(1-r) a+r b$ and $w=(1-r) u+r v$, where $r$ is a complex number, then the two triangles\\\\",
    "reference": "\n\n(1985, 2M) ",
    "options": [
        "a) have the same area\\\\",
        "b) are similar\\\\",
        "c) are congruent\\\\",
        "d) None of these"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Since $a, b, c$ and $u, v, w$ are the vertices of two triangles.\\nAlso,\\n$$\\begin{array}{lr}\\text { Also, } & c=(1-r) a+r b \\\\ \\text { and } & w=(1-r) u+r v\\end{array}$$\\nConsider $\\left|\\begin{array}{lll}a & u & 1 \\\\ b & v & 1 \\\\ c & w & 1\\end{array}\\right|$\\nApplying $R_3 \\rightarrow R_3-\\left\\{(1-r) R_1+r R_2\\right\\}$\\n$$\\begin{aligned}& =\\left|\\begin{array}{ccc}a & u & 1 \\\\ b & v & 1 \\\\ c-(1-r) a-r b & w-(1-r) u-r v & 1-(1-r)-r\\end{array}\\right| \\\\ & =\\left|\\begin{array}{lll}a & u & 1 \\\\ b & v & 1 \\\\ 0 & 0 & 0\\end{array}\\right|=0 \\\\ & \\end{aligned}$$ [from Eq. (i)]",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 340,
    "question": "Let $z=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}+\\frac{i}{2}^{5}+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}-\\frac{i}{2}^{5}$. If $R(z)$ and $I(z)$ respectively denote the real and imaginary parts of $z$, then\\\\",
    "reference": " \n\n(2019 Main, 10 Jan II)",
    "options": [
        "a) $R(z)>0$ and $I(z)>0$\\\\",
        "b) $I(z)=0$\\\\",
        "c) $R(z)<0$ and $I(z)>0$\\\\",
        "d) $R(z)=-3$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(b)",
    "solution": "Given, $z=\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}+\\frac{i}{2}^{5}+\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}-\\frac{i}{2}^{5}$\n\n$\\because$ Euler's form of\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n& \\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}+\\frac{i}{2}=\\cos \\frac{\\pi}{6}+i \\sin \\frac{\\pi}{6}=e^{i(\\pi / 6)} \\\\\n& \\text { and } \\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}-\\frac{i}{2}=\\cos \\frac{-\\pi}{6}+i \\sin -\\frac{\\pi}{6}=e^{-i \\pi / 6} \\\\\n& \\text { So, } \\quad z=\\left(e^{i \\pi / 6}\\right)^{5}+\\left(e^{-i \\pi / 6}\\right)^{5}=e^{i \\frac{5 \\pi}{6}}+e^{-i \\frac{5 \\pi}{6}} \\\\\n& =\\cos \\frac{5 \\pi}{6}+i \\sin \\frac{5 \\pi}{6}+\\cos \\frac{5 \\pi}{6}-i \\sin \\frac{5 \\pi}{6} \\\\\n& =2 \\cos \\frac{5 \\pi}{6} \\quad\\left[\\because e^{i \\theta}=\\cos \\theta+i \\sin \\theta\\right] \\\\\n& \\therefore \\quad I(z)=0 \\text { and } R(z)=-2 \\cos \\frac{\\pi}{6}=-\\sqrt{3}<0 \\\\\n& \\because \\cos \\frac{5 \\pi}{6}=\\cos \\pi-\\frac{\\pi}{6}=-\\cos \\frac{\\pi}{6}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 30,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 341,
    "question": "A particle $P$ starts from the point $z_{0}=1+2 i$, where $i=\\sqrt{-1}$. It moves first horizontally away from origin by 5 units and then vertically away from origin by 3 units to reach a point $z_{1}$. From $z_{1}$ the particle moves $\\sqrt{2}$ units in the direction of the vector $\\hat{\\mathbf{i}}+\\hat{\\mathbf{j}}$ and then it moves through an angle $\\frac{\\pi}{2}$ in anti-clockwise direction on a circle with centre at origin, to reach a point $z_{2}$. The point $z_{2}$ is given by\\\\",
    "reference": "\n\n(2008, 3M) ",
    "options": [
        "a) $6+7 i$\\\\",
        "b) $-7+6 i$\\\\",
        "c) $7+6 i$\\\\",
        "d) $-6+7 i$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-20(3)}\n\\end{center}\n\n$z_{2}^{\\prime}=\\left(6+\\sqrt{2} \\cos 45^{\\circ}, 5+\\sqrt{2} \\sin 45^{\\circ}\\right)=(7,6)=7+6 i$\n\nBy rotation about $(0,0)$,\n\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n\\frac{z_{2}}{z_{2}^{\\prime}} & =e^{i \\pi / 2} \\Rightarrow z_{2}=z_{2}^{\\prime} e^{i \\frac{\\pi}{2}} \\\\\n& =(7+6 i) \\cos \\frac{\\pi}{2}+i \\sin \\frac{\\pi}{2}=(7+6 i)(i)=-6+7 i\n\\end{aligned}\n$$",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 31,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 342,
    "question": "A man walks a distance of 3 units from the origin towards the North-East $\\left(\\mathrm{N} 45^{\\circ} \\mathrm{E}\\right)$ direction. From there, he walks a distance of 4 units towards the North-West $\\left(\\mathrm{N} 45^{\\circ} \\mathrm{W}\\right)$ direction to reach a point $P$. Then, the position of $P$ in the Argand plane is\\\\",
    "reference": " \n\n(2007, 3M)",
    "options": [
        "a) $3 e^{i \\pi / 4}+4 i$\\\\",
        "b) $(3-4 i) e^{i \\pi / 4}$\\\\",
        "c) $(4+3 i) e^{i \\pi / 4}$\\\\",
        "d) $(3+4 i) e^{i \\pi / 4}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "Let $O A=3$, so that the complex number associated with $A$ is $3 e^{i \\pi / 4}$. If $z$ is the complex number associated with $P$, then\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{rlrl} \n& & \\frac{z-3 e^{i \\pi / 4}}{0-3 e^{i \\pi / 4}} & =\\frac{4}{3} e^{-i \\pi / 2}=-\\frac{4 i}{3} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & 3 z-9 e^{i \\pi / 4} & =12 i e^{i \\pi / 4} \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & & z & =(3+4 i) e^{i \\pi / 4}\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\n\\begin{center}\n\\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_07_1585177dc772a224010eg-20(2)}\n\\end{center}",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 31,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 343,
    "question": "The shaded region, where $P=(-1,0), Q=(-1+\\sqrt{2}, \\sqrt{2})$ $R=(-1+\\sqrt{2},-\\sqrt{2}), S=(1,0)$ is represented by $(2005,1 \\mathrm{M})$\n\\begin{center}\n  \\includegraphics[max width=\\textwidth]{2024_07_13_552849a1aa1f7a6087f2g-08}\n  \\end{center}",
    "reference": "2005 ",
    "options": [
        "a) |z+1|>2,|\\arg (z+1)|<\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\\\",
        "b) |z+1|<2,|\\arg (z+1)|<\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\\\",
        "c) |z+1|>2,|\\arg (z+1)|>\\frac{\\pi}{4} \\\\",
        "d) |z-1|<2,|\\arg (z+1)|>\\frac{\\pi}{2}"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(a)",
    "solution": "Since, $|P Q|=|P S|=|P R|=2$\n\n$\\therefore \\quad$ Shaded part represents the external part of circle having centre $(-1,0)$ and radius 2 .\n\nAs we know equation of circle having centre $z_{0}$ and radius $r$, is $\\left|z-z_{0}\\right|=r$\n\n$$\n\\begin{array}{ll}\n\\therefore & |z-(-1+0 i)|>2 \\\\\n\\Rightarrow & |z+1|>2\n\\end{array}\n$$\n\nAlso, argument of $z+1$ with respect to positive direction of $X$-axis is $\\pi / 4$.\n\n\n\\begin{equation*}\n\\therefore \\quad \\arg (z+1) \\leq \\frac{\\pi}{4} \\tag{i}\n\\end{equation*}\n\n\nand argument of $z+1$ in anticlockwise direction is $-\\pi / 4$.\n\n$\\therefore \\quad-\\pi / 4 \\leq \\arg (z+1)$\n\nFrom Eqs. (i) and (ii),\n\n\n\\begin{equation*}\n|\\arg (z+1)| \\leq \\pi / 4 \\tag{ii}\n\\end{equation*}",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 31,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},
{
    "id": 344,
    "question": "If $0<\\alpha<\\frac{\\pi}{2}$ is a fixed angle. If $P=(\\cos \\theta, \\sin \\theta)$ and $Q=\\{\\cos (\\alpha \\stackrel{2}{-}), \\sin (\\alpha-\\theta)\\}$, then $Q$ is obtained from $P$ by",
    "reference": "\n\n(2002, 2M) ",
    "options": [
        "a) clockwise rotation around origin through an angle $\\alpha$",
        "b) anti-clockwise rotation around origin through an angle $\\alpha$",
        "c) reflection in the line through origin with slope $\\tan \\alpha$",
        "d) reflection in the line through origin with slope $\\tan \\frac{\\alpha}{2}$"
    ],
    "question_type": "Objective Question I",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "solution": "In the Argand plane, $P$ is represented by $e^{i 0}$ and $Q$ is represented by $e^{i(\\alpha-\\theta)}$\n\nNow, rotation about a line with angle $\\alpha$ is given by $e^{\\theta} \\rightarrow e^{(\\alpha-\\theta)}$. Therefore, $Q$ is obtained from $P$ by reflection in the line making an angle $\\alpha$ /2.",
    "chapter": "Complex Numbers",
    "LessonId": 31,
    "courseName": "Complex Numbers"
},